<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>NIMBLE</title>
<link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/#category=R</link>
<atom:link href="https://r-nimble.org/blog/index-r.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>An R package for programming with BUGS models and compiling parts of R</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.31</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Version 1.4.0 of NIMBLE released, plus new quadrature-based functionality in nimbleQuad package</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-4-0-of-nimble-released.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ve released the newest version of NIMBLE on CRAN and on our <a href="https://r-nimble.org/">website</a>. NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC, Laplace approximation, and SMC).</p>
<p>Version 1.4.0 provides important new and improved functionality, plus some bug fixes and improved error trapping.</p>
<p>The new and improved functionality includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>A new INLA-like deterministic nested posterior approximation whose methodology borrows from both INLA and the extended latent Gaussian models approach of the <code>aghq</code> package in R. This new approximation and NIMBLE’s existing Laplace and AGHQ approximation now live in a new package, <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/nimbleQuad/index.html"><code>nimbleQuad</code></a>, rather than in the core <code>nimble</code> package.</li>
<li>A new system for computing and storing “derived quantities” during MCMC execution, allowing users to record additional quantities of interest at every saved MCMC iteration (i.e., following the thinning interval, or some other user-chosen interval). Derived quantities provided by NIMBLE include means, variances, model log-densities, and predictive nodes. Users can also define their own derived quantities.</li>
<li>Matrix exponential functionality via <code>expm</code> and <code>expAv</code>.</li>
<li>The ability to provide multiple code chunks to <code>nimbleCode</code> for greater flexibility in composing models.</li>
<li>Greatly improved efficiency and memory use of AD system and making efficiency improvements to Laplace/AGHQ approximation.</li>
</ul>
<p>In addition to the new and improved functionality above, other bug fixes, improved error trapping, and enhancements include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Removing some documentation references to “BUGS” when referring to models.</li>
<li>Allowing users to turn off <code>model$checkBasics</code> via a new option.</li>
<li>Better handling inconsistencies between <code>inits</code> and <code>dimensions</code>.</li>
<li>Making minor improvements to the Pólya-gamma sampler.</li>
<li>Generalizing the system of dynamically generating conjugate MCMC samplers, to allow for multivariate parameters of dependent distributions to have distinct sizes from the dependent node itself .</li>
<li>Making MCEM append new samples when increasing sample size using the ascent-based method, rather than starting a new sample.</li>
</ul>
<p>Please see the <a href="https://r-nimble.org/release-notes.html">release notes</a> on our website for more details.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-4-0-of-nimble-released.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>announcing the nimbleMacros package and the use of macros in NIMBLE models</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/announcing-the-nimblemacros-package-and-the-use-of-macros-in-nimble-models.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Recent versions of NIMBLE now include the ability to use macros in models. NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC, Laplace approximation, and SMC).</p>
<p>A NIMBLE macro is a succinct syntax that expands to create the NIMBLE model code for part or all of a model.</p>
<p>We recently released the first version of the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/nimbleMacros/index.html"><code>nimbleMacros</code> package on CRAN</a>, which provides an initial set of macros available to users and developers. As an example, one could set up the code for a linear mixed effects model by using the <code>LM</code> (“linear model”) macro like this:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(nimbleMacros)</span>
<span id="cb1-2">code <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">nimbleCode</span>({</span>
<span id="cb1-3">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">LM</span>(weight[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span>N] <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">~</span> Time <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> (<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">|</span>Chick))</span>
<span id="cb1-4">})</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<p>with the formula syntax mimicking that of the lme4 package. After building the model based on the <code>code</code> object, you can see the model code produced after the macro is expanded with <code>model$getCode()</code>. The nimbleMacros package also includes macros for creating linear predictors and for loops, and we plan to add additional macros in the future.</p>
<p>Developers can use the tools in <code>nimble</code> itself to create their own macros. See <a href="https://r-nimble.org/html_manual/cha-user-defined.html#sec:user-macros">Section 12.4 of the NIMBLE user manual</a>, <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/nimbleMacros/vignettes/nimbleMacros.html">the <code>nimbleMacros</code> vignette</a>, or <code>help(buildMacro)</code> for more information.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/announcing-the-nimblemacros-package-and-the-use-of-macros-in-nimble-models.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Version 1.3.0 of NIMBLE released</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-3-0-of-nimble-released.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ve released the newest version of NIMBLE on CRAN and on our <a href="https://r-nimble.org/">website</a>. NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC, Laplace approximation, and SMC).</p>
<p>Version 1.3.0 provides some new and improved functionality, plus some bug fixes and improved error trapping.</p>
<p>The new and improved functionality includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>A new multivariate sampler, the Barker proposal sampler (<code>sampler_barker</code>). We encourage users to try this sampler in place of the block Metropolis <code>RW_block</code> sampler and let us know how well it works. The Barker sampler uses gradient information and may improve adaptation behavior, including<br>
better mixing when parameters are on different scales or the initialproposal scale is too large.</li>
<li>An improved Laplace/AGHQ implementation that includes use of the <code>nlminb</code> optimizer for both inner and outer optimization (for better optimization performance), improved messaging and output naming, returning the log-likelihood and degrees of freedom for model selection calculations, and unified control of optimization method and other controls at either the build stage or through the <code>updateSettings</code> method.</li>
<li>The addition of the BOBYQA optimization method through <code>nimOptim</code>, registered via <code>nimOptimMethod</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p>In addition to the new and improved functionality above, other bug fixes, improved error trapping, and enhancements include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Preventing the use of nimbleFunction method names and nimbleFunction names that conflict with names in the nimble language (DSL).</li>
<li>More carefully checking for and warning of cases of NaN and non-finite log probability values in various samplers that in some cases may indicate invalid MCMC sampling.</li>
<li>More carefully handling of NaN and non-finite log probability values in the CRP sampler.</li>
<li>Error trapping cases of dynamic indices producing a non-scalar result in AD-enabled models and provide a suggested work-around.</li>
<li>Error trapping use of a non-existent nimbleList.</li>
<li>Preventing use of a single seed when running multiple chains via <code>runMCMC</code>.</li>
<li>Improving messaging related to lack of derivative support for functions.</li>
<li>Adding information about model macros to the manual.</li>
<li>Fixing bug in caching values in the CRP sampler when maximum number of clusters is exceeded, which would have caused incorrect sampling (albeit with the user having been warned that they should increase the maximum number of clusters).</li>
<li>Fixing an issue preventing use of nimbleList elements in <code>nimCat</code>.</li>
<li>Preventing an adaptation interval of one for various block samplers for which an interval of one leads to an error.</li>
<li>Allowing <code>runLaplace</code> to use an uncompiled Laplace object.</li>
</ul>
<p>Please see the <a href="https://r-nimble.org/more/news">release notes</a> on our website for more details.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-3-0-of-nimble-released.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Version 1.2.1 of NIMBLE released</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-2-1-of-nimble-released.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ve released the newest version of NIMBLE on CRAN and on our <a href="https://r-nimble.org/">website</a>. NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC, Laplace approximation, and SMC).</p>
<p>This is a micro release that primarily addresses some packaging changes requested by CRAN. In addition, this release includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>A multinomial MCMC sampler, <code>sampler_RW_multinomial</code>, for random variables following a multinomial distribution.</li>
<li>Some enhancements to error trapping and warning messages.</li>
<li>A variety of minor bug fixes.</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-2-1-of-nimble-released.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Version 1.1.0 of NIMBLE released</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-1-0-of-nimble-released.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ve released the newest version of NIMBLE on CRAN and on our <a href="https://r-nimble.org/">website</a>. NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC,Laplace approximation, and SMC).</p>
<p>This release provides new functionality as well as various bug fixes and improved error trapping, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Improving our automatic differentiation (AD) system so it can be used in a wider range of models, including models with stochastic indexing, discrete latent states, and CAR distributions. Support for AD for these models means that HMC sampling and Laplace approximation can be used.</li>
<li>Allowing distributions and functions (whether user-defined or built-in) that lack AD support (such as <code>dinterval</code>, <code>dconstraint</code>, and truncated distributions) to be used and compiled in AD-enabled models. The added flexibility increases the range of models in which one can use AD methods (HMC or Laplace) on some parts of a model and other samplers or methods on other parts.</li>
<li>Adding <code>nimIntegrate</code> to the NIMBLE language, providing one-dimensional numerical integration via adaptive quadrature, equivalent to R’s <code>integrate</code>. This can, for example, be used in a user-defined function or distribution for use in model code, such as to implement certain point process or survival models that involve a one-dimensional integral.</li>
<li>Adding a “prior samples” MCMC sampler, which uses an existing set of numerical samples to define the prior distribution of model node(s).</li>
<li>Better support of the dCRP distribution in non-standard model structures.</li>
<li>Adding error trapping to prevent accidental use of C++ keywords as model variable names.</li>
<li>Removing the <code>RW_multinomial</code> MCMC sampler, which was found to generate incorrect posterior results (in cases when a latent state followed a multinomial distribution)</li>
<li>Fixing a bug in conjugacy checking in a case of subsets of multivariate nodes.</li>
<li>Fixing <code>is.na</code> and <code>is.nan</code> to operate in the expected vectorized fashion.</li>
<li>Improving documentation of AD, nimbleHMC, and nimbleSMC in the manual.</li>
<li>Updating Eigen (the C++ linear algebra library used by nimble) to version 3.4.0.</li>
</ul>
<p>Please see the <a href="https://r-nimble.org/more/news">release notes</a> on our website for more details.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-1-0-of-nimble-released.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>nimbleHMC version 0.2.0 released, providing improved HMC performance</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/nimblehmc-version-0-2-0-released-providing-improved-hmc-performance.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>nimbleHMC provides Hamiltonian Monte Carlo samplers for use with NIMBLE, in particular NUTS samplers. NIMBLE’s HMC samplers can be flexibly assigned to a subset of model parameters, allowing users to consider various sampling configurations.</p>
<p>We’ve released version 0.2.0 of nimbleHMC, which includes a new default NUTS sampler inspired by Stan’s implementation of NUTS. It also provides an updated version of our previous NUTS sampler (which is based on the original Hoffman and Gelman paper, and is now called the ‘NUTS_classic’ sampler in NIMBLE) that fixes performance issues in version 0.1.1.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/nimblehmc-version-0-2-0-released-providing-improved-hmc-performance.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Version 1.0.1 of NIMBLE released, fixing a bug in version 1.0.0 affecting certain models</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-0-1-of-nimble-released-fixing-a-bug-in-version-1-0-0-affecting-certain-models.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ve released the newest version of NIMBLE on CRAN and on our website. NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC and SMC).</p>
<p>Version 1.0.1 follows shortly after 1.0.0 and fixes an issue and a bug introduced in version 1.0.0 causing data to be set incorrectly in certain models.</p>
<p>Both cases occur only when a variable (e.g., <code>x</code>) contains both stochastic nodes (e.g.&nbsp;<code>x[2] ~ &lt;some distribution&gt;</code>) and <em>either</em> deterministic nodes (e.g.&nbsp;<code>x[3] &lt;- &lt;some calculation&gt;</code>) or right-hand-side-only nodes (e.g.&nbsp;<code>x[4]</code> appears only on the right-hand-side, like an explanatory value).</p>
<p>The issue involves a change of behavior (relative to previous nimble versions) when both setting data values for some nodes and initial values for other nodes within the same variable (that satisfies the previous condition). Data values for right-hand-side-only nodes were replaced by initial values (inits) if both were provided. Version 1.0.1 reverts to previous behavior that data values are not replaced by initial values in that situation.</p>
<p>The bug involves models where (for a variable satisfying the previous condition) not every scalar element within the variable is used as a node and some of the nodes in the variable are data. In that situation, data values may be set incorrectly. This could typically occur in models with autoregressive structure directly on some data nodes (such as may be the case for capture-recapture models involving many individual capture histories within the same variable, indexed by individual and time, with some individuals not present for the entire time series, resulting in unused scalar elements of the variable).</p>
<p>Please see the <a href="https://r-nimble.org/more/news">release notes</a> on our website for more details.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-0-1-of-nimble-released-fixing-a-bug-in-version-1-0-0-affecting-certain-models.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Version 1.0.0 of NIMBLE released, providing automatic differentiation, Laplace approximation, and HMC sampling</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-0-0-of-nimble-released-providing-automatic-differentiation-laplace-approximation-and-hmc-sampling.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ve released the newest version of NIMBLE on CRAN and on our <a href="https://r-nimble.org/">website</a>. NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC and SMC).</p>
<p>Version 1.0.0 provides substantial new functionality. This includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>A Laplace approximation algorithm that allows one to find the MLE for model parameters based on approximating the marginal likelihood in models with continuous random effects/latent process values.</li>
<li>A Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC) MCMC sampler implementing the NUTS algorithm (available in the newly-released <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/nimbleHMC/index.html">nimbleHMC</a> package).</li>
<li>Support in NIMBLE’s algorithm programming system to obtain derivatives of functions and arbitrary calculations within models.</li>
<li>A parameter transformation system allowing algorithms to work in unconstrained parameter spaces when model parameters have constrained domains.</li>
</ul>
<p>These are documented via the R help system and <a href="https://r-nimble.org/html_manual/cha-AD.html">a new section at the end of our User Manual</a>. We’re excited for users to try out the new features and let us know of their experiences. In particular, given these major additions to the NIMBLE system, we anticipate the possibility of minor glitches. The best place to reach out for support is still the <a href="https://r-nimble.org/more/issues-and-groups">nimble-users list</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the new functionality above, other enhancements and bug fixes include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Fixing a bug (previously reported in a nimble-users message) giving incorrect results in NIMBLE’s cross-validation function (<code>runCrossValidate</code>) for all but the ‘predictive’ loss function for NIMBLE versions 0.10.0 – 0.13.2.</li>
<li>Fixing a bug in conjugacy checking causing incorrect identification of conjugate relationships in models with unusual uses of subsets, supersets, and slices of multivariate normal nodes.</li>
<li>Improving control of the <code>addSampler</code> method for MCMC.</li>
<li>Improving the WAIC system in a few small ways.</li>
<li>Enhancing error trapping and warning messages.</li>
</ul>
<p>Please see the <a href="https://github.com/nimble-dev/nimble/blob/devel/packages/nimble/inst/NEWS.md">NEWS file</a> in the package source for more details.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-1-0-0-of-nimble-released-providing-automatic-differentiation-laplace-approximation-and-hmc-sampling.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Version 0.13.1 of NIMBLE released</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-0-13-1-of-nimble-released.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ve released the newest version of NIMBLE on CRAN and on our website. This version is purely a bug fix release that fixes <a href="https://r-nimble.org/bug-in-newly-released-version-0-13-0-affecting-mcmc-for-models-with-predictive-nodes">a bug introduced in our new handling of predictive nodes in version 0.13.0</a> (released in November). If you installed version 0.13.0, please upgrade to 0.13.1.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-0-13-1-of-nimble-released.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bug in newly-released version 0.13.0 affecting MCMC for models with predictive nodes</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/bug-in-newly-released-version-0-13-0-affecting-mcmc-for-models-with-predictive-nodes.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We recently released version 0.13.0, which has some improvements in how we handle predictive nodes in NIMBLE’s MCMC engine.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, we realized (thanks to a user post from a couple days ago) that there is a bug in this new approach to predictive nodes.</p>
<p>If you haven’t upgraded to version 0.13.0, simply wait to upgrade until we release a bug fix in 0.13.1 in the next couple weeks.</p>
<p>If you have upgraded to version 0.13.0 and if you have run an MCMC on a model that both (1) has predictive nodes and (2) has multivariate nodes, then the bug might affect your results. Please set:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">nimbleOptions</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">MCMCusePredictiveDependenciesInCalculations =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">TRUE</span>)</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<p>and then reconfigure/rebuild and rerun your MCMC. The option above will ensure that the MCMC behaves as it would in previous versions of NIMBLE.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/bug-in-newly-released-version-0-13-0-affecting-mcmc-for-models-with-predictive-nodes.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Version 0.13.0 of NIMBLE released</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-0-13-0-of-nimble-released.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ve released the newest version of NIMBLE on CRAN and on our <a href="https://r-nimble.org/">website</a>. NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC and SMC).</p>
<p>Version 0.13.0 provides new functionality (in particular improved handling of predictive nodes in MCMC) and minor bug fixes, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Thoroughly revamping handling of posterior predictive nodes in the MCMC system, in particular that MCMC samplers, by default, will now exclude predictive dependencies from internal sampler calculations. This should improve MCMC mixing for models with predictive nodes. Posterior predictive nodes are now sampled conditional on all other model nodes at the end of each MCMC iteration.</li>
<li>Adding functionality to the MCMC configuration system, including a new <code>replaceSamplers</code> method and updates to the arguments for the <code>addSamplers</code> method.</li>
<li>Adding an option to the WAIC system to allow additional burnin (in addition to standard MCMC burnin) before calculating online WAIC, thereby allowing inspection of initial samples without forcing them to be used for WAIC.</li>
<li>Warning users of unused constants during model building.</li>
<li>Fixing bugs that prevented use of variables starting with “logProb” or named “i” in model code.</li>
<li>Fixing a bug to prevent infinite recursion in particular cases in conjugacy checking.</li>
<li>Fixing a bug in simulating from <code>dcar_normal</code> nodes when multiple nodes passed to simulate.</li>
</ul>
<p>Please see the <a href="https://r-nimble.org/more/news">release notes</a> on our website for more details.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-0-13-0-of-nimble-released.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>We’re looking for a programmer</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/were-looking-for-a-programmer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The NIMBLE project anticipates having some funding for a part-time programmer to implement statistical algorithms and make improvements in nimble’s core code. Examples may include building adaptive Gaussian quadrature in nimble’s programming system and expanding nimble’s hierarchical model system. Remote work is possible. This is not a formal job solicitation, but please send a CV/resume to nimble.stats@gmail.com if you are interested so we can have you on our list. Important skills will be experience with hierarchical statistical modeling algorithms, R programming, and nimble itself. Experience with C++ will be helpful but not required.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/were-looking-for-a-programmer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>NIMBLE virtual short course, January 4-6, 2023</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/nimble-virtual-short-course-january-4-6-2023.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ll be holding a virtual training workshop on <a href="http://r-nimble.org/">NIMBLE</a>, January 4-6, 2023 from 8 am to 1 pm US Pacific (California) time each day. NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC and SMC).</p>
<p>Recently we added support for automatic differentiation (AD) to NIMBLE in a <a href="https://r-nimble.org/beta-version-of-nimble-with-automatic-differentiation-including-hmc-sampling-and-laplace-approximation">beta release</a>, and the workshop will cover NIMBLE’s AD capabilities in detail.</p>
<p>The workshop will cover the following material:</p>
<ul>
<li>the basic concepts and workflows for using NIMBLE and converting BUGS or JAGS models to work in NIMBLE.</li>
<li>overview of different MCMC sampling strategies and how to use them in NIMBLE, including Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC).</li>
<li>writing new distributions and functions for more flexible modeling and more efficient computation.</li>
<li>tips and tricks for improving computational efficiency.</li>
<li>using advanced model components, including Bayesian non-parametric distributions (based on Dirichlet process priors), conditional auto-regressive (CAR) models for spatially correlated random fields, Laplace approximation, and reversible jump samplers for variable selection.</li>
<li>an introduction to programming new algorithms in NIMBLE.</li>
<li>use of automatic differentiation (AD) in algorithms.</li>
<li>calling R and compiled C++ code from compiled NIMBLE models or functions.</li>
</ul>
<p>If you are interested in attending, please <a href="https://forms.gle/8NuUcDJtMUGxCHv78">pre-register</a>. Registration fees will be $125 (regular) or $50 (student). We are also offering a process (see the pre-registration form) for students to request a fee waiver.</p>
<p>The workshop will assume attendees have a basic understanding of hierarchical/Bayesian models and MCMC, the BUGS (or JAGS) model language, and some familiarity with R.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>education</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/nimble-virtual-short-course-january-4-6-2023.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beta version of NIMBLE with automatic differentiation, including HMC sampling and Laplace approximation</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/beta-version-of-nimble-with-automatic-differentiation-including-hmc-sampling-and-laplace-approximation.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’re excited to announce that NIMBLE now supports automatic differentiation (AD), also known as algorithmic differentiation, in a <a href="https://r-nimble.org/ad-beta">beta version available on our website</a>. In this beta version, NIMBLE now provides:</p>
<ul>
<li>Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC) sampling for an entire parameter vector or arbitrary subsets of the parameter vector (i.e., combined with other samplers for the remaining parameters).</li>
<li>Laplace approximation for approximate integration over latent states in a model, allowing maximum likelihood estimation and MCMC based on the marginal likelihood (via the RW_llFunction samplers).</li>
<li>The ability for users and algorithm developers to write nimbleFunctions that calculate derivatives of functions, including many but not all mathematical operations that are supported in the NIMBLE language.</li>
</ul>
<p>We’re making this beta release available to allow our users to test and evaluate the AD functionality and the new algorithms, but it is not recommended for production use at this stage. So please give it a try, and let us know of any problems or suggestions you have, either via the <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/nimble-users">nimble-users list</a>, <a href="https://github.com/nimble-dev/nimble/issues">bug reports to our GitHub repository</a>, or email to <a href="mailto:nimble.stats@gmail.com">nimble.stats@gmail.com</a>.</p>
<p>You can download the <a href="https://r-nimble.org/ad-beta">beta version</a> and view an [extensive draft manual]https://r-nimble.org/ADuserManual_draft/chapter_AD.html) for the AD functionality.</p>
<p>We plan to release this functionality in the next NIMBLE release on CRAN in the coming months.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/beta-version-of-nimble-with-automatic-differentiation-including-hmc-sampling-and-laplace-approximation.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Version 0.12.2 of NIMBLE released, including an important bug fix for some models using Bayesian nonparametrics with the dCRP distribution</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-0-12-2-of-nimble-released-including-an-important-bug-fix-for-some-models-using-bayesian-nonparametrics-with-the-dcrp-distribution.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ve released the newest version of NIMBLE on CRAN and on our website. NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC and SMC).</p>
<p>Version 0.12.2 is a bug fix release. In particular, this release fixes a bug in our Bayesian nonparametric distribution (BNP) functionality that gives incorrect MCMC results for some models, specifically when using the dCRP distribution when the parameters of the mixture components (i.e., the clusters) have hyperparameters (i.e., the base measure parameters) that are unknown and sampled during the MCMC. Here is an example basic model structure that is affected by the bug:</p>
<p><code>k[1:n] ~ dCRP(alpha, n) for(i in 1:n) {     y[i] ~ dnorm(mu[k[i]], 1)     mu[i] ~ dnorm(mu0, 1) ## mixture component parameters with hyperparameter } mu0 ~ dnorm(0, 1) ## unknown cluster hyperparameter</code></p>
<p>(There is no problem without the hyperparameter layer - i.e., if <code>mu0</code> is a fixed value – which is the situation in many models.)</p>
<p>We strongly encourage users using models with this type of structure to rerun their analyses, and we apologize for this issue.</p>
<p>Other changes in this release include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Fixing an issue with reversible jump variable selection under a similar situation to the BNP issue discussed above (in particular where there are unknown hyperparameters of the regression coefficients being considered, which would likely be an unusual use case).</li>
<li>Fixing a bug preventing setup of conjugate samplers for dwishart or dinvwishart nodes when using dynamic indexing.</li>
<li>Fixing a bug preventing use of truncation bounds specified via <code>data</code> or <code>constants</code>.</li>
<li>Fixing a bug preventing MCMC sampling with the LKJ prior for 2×2 matrices.</li>
<li>Fixing a bug in <code>runCrossValidate</code> affecting extraction of multivariate nodes.</li>
<li>Fixing a bug producing incorrect subset assignment into logical vectors in nimbleFunction code.</li>
<li>Fixing a bug preventing use of <code>nimbleExternalCall</code> with a constant expression.</li>
<li>Fixing a bug preventing use of recursion in nimbleFunctions without setup code.</li>
</ul>
<p>Please see the <a href="https://r-nimble.org/more/news">release notes</a> on our website for more details.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-0-12-2-of-nimble-released-including-an-important-bug-fix-for-some-models-using-bayesian-nonparametrics-with-the-dcrp-distribution.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>NIMBLE in-person short course, June 1-3, Lisbon, Portugal</title>
  <dc:creator>Chris Paciorek</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/nimble-in-person-short-course-june-1-3-lisbon-portugal.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ll be holding a in-person training workshop on NIMBLE, June 1-3, 2022, in Lisbon, Portugal, sponsored by the Centro de Estatística e Aplicações at the Universidade Lisboa (CEAUL).</p>
<p>NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC and SMC).</p>
<p>More details and registration are available at the <a href="https://nimbleworkshop.weebly.com/">workshop website</a>. No previous NIMBLE experience is required, but the workshop will assume some familiarity with hierarchical models, Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC), and R.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>education</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/nimble-in-person-short-course-june-1-3-lisbon-portugal.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A close look at some linear model MCMC comparisons</title>
  <dc:creator>Perry de Valpine</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/a-close-look-at-some-linear-model-mcmc-comparisons.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This is our second blog post taking a careful look at some of the results posted in an <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.09357">arXiv manuscript by Beraha, Falco, and Guglielmi (BFG)</a>. They compare JAGS, Stan, and NIMBLE using four examples. In their results, each package performs best in at least one example.</p>
<p>In our <a href="https://r-nimble.org/a-close-look-at-some-posted-trials-of-nimble-for-accelerated-failure-time-models">previous post</a>, we explained that they compared apples to oranges in the accelerated failure time (AFT) example. They gave Stan a different and easier problem than they gave JAGS and NIMBLE. When we gave NIMBLE the same problem, we saw that its MCMC performance was up to 45 times better than what they reported. We looked first at the AFT example because that’s where NIMBLE seemed to perform comparatively worst.</p>
<p>In this post we’re looking at the simple linear model example. <strong>It turns out that the models were written more efficiently for Stan than for JAGS and NIMBLE</strong> , because matrix multiplication was used for Stan but all scalar steps of matrix multiplication were written in JAGS and NIMBLE. JAGS and NIMBLE do support matrix multiplication and inner products. <strong>When we modify the models to also use matrix multiplication, NIMBLE’s MCMC performance with default samplers increases often by 1.2 to 3-fold but sometimes by 5 to &gt;10-fold over what was reported</strong> by BFG, as far as we can tell. This had to do with both raw computational efficiency and also MCMC samplers invoked by different ways to write the model code. Other issues are described below.</p>
<p>BFG’s linear model examples explore different data sizes (n = 30, 100, 1000, or in one case 2000), different numbers of explanatory variables (4, 16, 30, 50 or 100), and different priors for the variance and/or coefficients (beta[i]s), all in a simple linear model. The priors included:</p>
<ul>
<li>“LM-C”: an inverse gamma prior for variance, which is used for both residual variance and variance of normal priors for beta[i]s (regression coefficients). This setup should offer conjugate sampling for both the variance parameter and the beta[i]s.</li>
<li>“LM-C Bin”: the same prior as “LM-C”. This case has Bernoulli- instead of normally-distributed explanatory variables in the data simulations. It’s very similar to “LM-C”.</li>
<li>“LM-WI”: A weakly informative (“WI”) prior for residual standard deviation using a truncated, scaled t-distribution. beta[i]s have a non-informative (sd = 100) normal prior.</li>
<li>“LM-NI”: A non-informative (“NI”) flat prior for residual standard deviation. beta[i]s have a non-informative (sd = 100) normal prior.</li>
<li>“LM-L”: A lasso (“L”) prior for beta[i]s. This uses a double-exponential prior for beta[i]s, with a parameter that itself follows an exponential prior. This prior is a Bayesian analog of the lasso for variable selection, so the scenarios used for this have large numbers of explanatory variables, with different numbers of them (z) set to 0 in the simulations. Residual variance has an inverse gamma prior.</li>
</ul>
<p>Again, we are going to stick to NIMBLE here and not try to reproduce or explore results for JAGS or Stan.</p>
<p>In more detail, the big issues that jumped out from BFG’s code are:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Stan was given matrix multiplication for <code>X %*% beta</code>, while NIMBLE and JAGS were given code to do all of the element-by-element steps of matrix multiplication.</strong> Both NIMBLE and JAGS support matrix multiplication and inner products, so we think it is better and more directly comparable to use these features.</li>
<li>For the “LM-C” and “LM-C Bin” cases, the prior for the beta[i]s was given as a multivariate normal with a diagonal covariance matrix. It is better (and equivalent) to give each element a univariate normal prior.</li>
</ol>
<p>There are two reasons that writing out matrix multiplication as they did is not a great way to code a model. The first is that it is just inefficient. For X that is N-by-p and beta that is p-by-1, there are N*p scalar multiplications and N summations of length p in the model code. Although somewhere in the computer those elemental steps need to be taken, they will be substantially faster if not broken up by hand-coding them. When NIMBLE generates (and then compiles) C++, it generates C++ for the Eigen linear algebra library, which gives efficient implementations of matrix operations.</p>
<p>The second reason, however, may be more important in this case. Using either matrix multiplication or inner products makes it easier for NIMBLE to determine that the coefficients (“beta[i]”s) in many of these cases have conjugate relationships that can be used for Gibbs sampling. The way BFG wrote the model revealed to us that we’re not detecting the conjugacy in this case. That’s something we plan to fix, but it’s not a situation that’s come before us yet. Detecting conjugacy in a graphical model — as written in the BUGS/JAGS/NIMBLE dialects of the BUGS language — involves symbolic algebra, so it’s difficult to catch all cases.</p>
<p>The reasons it’s better to give a set of univariate normal priors than a single multivariate normal are similar. It’s more computationally efficient, and it makes it easier to detect conjugacy.</p>
<p>In summary, they wrote the model inefficiently for NIMBLE and differently between packages, and we didn’t detect conjugacy for the way they wrote it. In the results below, the “better” results use matrix multiplication directly (in all cases) and use univariate normal priors instead of a multivariate normal (in the “LM-C” and “LM-C Bin” cases).</p>
<p>It also turns out that neither JAGS nor NIMBLE detects conjugacy for the precision parameter of the “LM-C” and “LM-C Bin” cases. (This is shown by list.samplers in rjags and configureMCMC in NIMBLE.) In NIMBLE, a summary of how conjugacy is determined is in Table 7.1 of our User Manual. It can be obtained by changing <code>sd = sigma</code> to <code>var = sigmasq</code> in one line of BFG’s code. In these examples, we found that this issue doesn’t make much different to MCMC efficiency, so we leave it as they coded it.</p>
<p>Before giving our results, we’ll make a few observations on BFG’s results, shown in their Table 2. One is that JAGS gives very efficient sampling for many of these cases, and that’s something we’ve seen before. Especially when conjugate sampling is available, JAGS does well. Next is that Stan and NIMBLE each do better than the other in some cases. As we wrote about in the previous post, BFG chose not to calculate what we see as the most relevant metric for comparison. That is the rate of generating effectively independent samples, the ESS/time, which we call MCMC efficiency. An MCMC system can be efficient by slowly generating well-mixed samples or by rapidly generating poorly-mixed samples. One has to make choices such as whether burn-in (or warmup) time is counted in the denominator, depending on exactly what is of interest. BFG reported only ESS/recorded iterations and total iterations/time. The product of these is a measure of ESS/time, scaled by a ratio of total iterations / recorded iterations.</p>
<p>For example, in the “LM-C” case with “N = 1000, p = 4”, Stan has (ESS/recorded iterations) * (total iterations/time) = 0.99 * 157=155, while NIMBLE has 0.14 * 1571=220. Thus in this case NIMBLE is generating effectively independent samples faster than Stan, because the faster computation out-weighs the poorer mixing. In other cases, Stan has higher ESS/time than NIMBLE. When BFG round ESS/recorded iterations to “1%” in some cases, the ESS/time is unknown up to a factor of 3 because 1% could be rounded from 0.50 or from 1.49. For most cases, Stan and NIMBLE are within a factor of 2 of each other, which is close. One case where Stan really stands out is the non-informative prior (LM-NI) with p&gt;n, but it’s worth noting that this is a statistically unhealthy case. With p&gt;n, parameters are not identifiable without the help of a prior. In the LM-NI case, the prior is uninformative, and the posteriors for beta[i]s are not much different than their priors.</p>
<p>One other result jumps out as strange from their Table 2. The run-time results for “LM-WI” (total iterations / time) are much, much slower than in other cases. For example, with N = 100 and p = 4, this case was only 2.6% (294 vs 11,000 ) as fast as the corresponding “LM-C” case. We’re not sure how that could make sense, so it was something we wanted to check.</p>
<p>We took all of <a href="https://github.com/daniele-falco/software_comparison/tree/main/linear_models">BFG’s source code</a> and <a href="https://github.com/nimble-dev/nimble-demos/tree/master/blog_posts/LM_comparisons_Beraha_etal">organized it to be more fully reproducible</a>. After our previous blog post, set.seed calls were added to their source code, so we use those. We also organize the code into functions and sets of runs to save and process together. We think we interpreted their code correctly, but we can’t be sure. For ESS estimation, we used <code>coda::effectiveSize</code>, but Stan and mcmcse are examples of packages with other methods, and we aren’t sure what BFG used. They thin by 2 and give average results for beta[i]s. We want to compare to their results, so we take those steps too.</p>
<p>Here are the results:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 11%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th></th>
<th style="text-align: right;">BFG</th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;">Better code</th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;">Improvement</th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td></td>
<td>ESS/Ns</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">Nit/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">ESS/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">ESS/Ns</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">Nit/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">ESS/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">Better by</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>LM-C</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=100, p=4</td>
<td>0.15</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">56122.45</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3738.90</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.03</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">23060.80</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">10842.00</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2.90</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=1000, p=4</td>
<td>0.14</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">9401.71</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">609.97</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.00</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2866.82</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1303.10</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2.14</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=100, p=16</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">25345.62</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">428.45</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.95</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5555.56</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2396.00</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5.59</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=1000, p=16</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3471.13</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">54.06</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.00</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">613.98</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">278.53</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5.15</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=2000, p=30</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">863.83</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5.52</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.00</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">137.60</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">62.67</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">11.35</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=30, p=50</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">11470.28</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">24.49</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.07</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3869.15</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">114.62</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4.68</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>LM-C Bin</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=100, p=4</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">61452.51</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3303.31</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.52</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">22916.67</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5384.40</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.63</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=1000, p=4</td>
<td>0.10</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">9945.75</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">441.07</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.47</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2857.14</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">606.16</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.37</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=100, p=16</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">26699.03</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">430.92</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.49</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5530.42</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1223.25</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2.84</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=1000, p=16</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3505.42</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">41.68</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.55</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">655.46</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">163.59</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3.92</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=30, p=50</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">11815.25</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">44.01</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.12</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3941.24</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">211.66</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4.81</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>LM-WI</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=100, p=4</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">44117.65</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5595.82</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.99</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">22865.85</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">7545.97</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.35</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=1000, p=4</td>
<td>0.44</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4874.88</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">709.03</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.98</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2834.47</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">929.87</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.31</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=100, p=16</td>
<td>0.32</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">11441.65</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1233.59</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.94</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5845.67</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1837.45</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.49</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=1000, p=16</td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1269.14</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">179.09</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.00</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">653.62</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">217.22</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.21</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>LM-NI</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=100, p=4</td>
<td>0.37</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">43604.65</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5415.31</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.01</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">22935.78</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">7749.15</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.43</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=1000, p=4</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5613.77</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">804.61</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.06</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2751.28</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">974.50</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.21</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=100, p=16</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">12386.46</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1298.40</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.94</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">6134.97</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1932.29</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.49</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=1000, p=16</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1271.83</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">182.56</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.02</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">625.94</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">212.29</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.16</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=30, p=50</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">8581.24</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">14.45</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.01</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3755.63</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">13.80</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.96</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>LM-Lasso</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=100, p=16, z=0</td>
<td>0.33</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">10881.39</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">905.68</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.33</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">17730.50</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1475.74</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.63</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=1000, p=16, z=0</td>
<td>0.44</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1219.59</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">132.65</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.44</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2129.02</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">231.57</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.75</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=1000, p=30, z=2</td>
<td>0.41</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">552.30</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">56.81</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.41</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">942.42</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">96.94</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.71</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=1000, p=30, z=15</td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">540.51</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">56.91</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.42</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">941.97</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">99.17</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.74</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=1000, p=30, z=28</td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">541.01</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">56.27</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.42</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">970.73</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">100.97</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.79</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=1000, p=100, z=2</td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">77.75</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">7.06</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.36</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">141.22</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">12.83</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.82</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>N=1000, p=100, z=50</td>
<td>0.37</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">74.89</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">6.89</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.37</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">141.32</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">13.01</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.89</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>N=1000, p=100, z=98</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">74.78</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">7.37</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.39</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">142.60</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">14.05</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.91</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The “BFG” columns gives results from the same way BFG ran the cases, we think. The “ESS/Ns” is the same as their <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cvarepsilon_%7B%5Ceta%7D">. ESS is averaged for the beta parameters. Ns is the number of saved samples, after burn-in and thinning. Their code gives different choices of burn-in and saved iterations for the different cases, and we used their settings. The “Nit/t” is the total number of iterations (including burn-in) divided by total computation time. The final column, which BFG don’t give, is “ESS/t”, what we call MCMC efficiency. Choice of time in the denominator includes burn-in time (the same as for “Nit/t”).</p>
<p>The “Better code” columns give results when we write the code with matrix multiplication and, for “LM-C” and “LM-C Bin”, univariate priors. It is almost as efficient to write the code using an inner product for each mu[i] instead of matrix multiplication for all mu[i] together. Matrix multiplication makes sense when all of the inputs that might changes (in this case, beta[i]s updated by MCMC) require all of the same likelihood contributions to be calculated from the result (in this case, all y[i]s from all mu[i]s). Either way of coding the model makes it easier for NIMBLE to sample the beta[i]s with conjugate samplers and avoids the inefficiency of putting every scalar step into the model code.</p>
<p>The “Better by” column gives the ratio of “ESS/t” for the “Better code” to “ESS/t” for the BFG code. This is the factor by which the “Better code” version improves upon the “BFG” version.</p>
<p>We can see that writing better code often give improvements of say 1.2-3.0 fold, and sometimes of 5-10+ fold in ESS/time. These improvements — which came from writing the model in NIMBLE more similarly to how it was written in Stan — often put NIMBLE closer to or faster than Stan in various cases, and sometimes faster than JAGS with BFG’s version of the model. We’re sticking to NIMBLE, so we haven’t run JAGS with the better-written code to see how much it improves. Stan still shines for p&gt;n, and JAGS is still really good at linear models. The results show that, for the first four categories (above the LM-Lasso results), NIMBLE also can achieve very good mixing (near 100% ESS/saved samples), with the exception of the p&gt;n cases. BFG’s results showed worse mixing for NIMBLE in those cases.</p>
<p>We can also see that BFG’s computation-time results for “LM-WI” (which we noted above) do appear to be really weird. In our results, that case ran somewhat slower than the LM-C cases with matching N and p, but not around 40-times slower as reported by BFG. We won’t make detailed comparisons of LM-WI cases because we’re not confident BFG’s results are solid for these.</p>
<p>As a example, take LM-C, with the simplest being “N=100, p=4” and the hardest being “N=2000, p=30”, not counting the p&gt;n case. For the simplest case, BFG report that JAGS is about 2.1 times more efficient than Stan and about 2.4 times more efficient than NIMBLE. (E.g., the 2.1 comes from (100 * 3667)/(96 * 1883), reading numbers from their Table 2.) By writing the model in the simpler, better way in NIMBLE, we see a 2.9 fold gain in efficiency. This would make NIMBLE more efficient than Stan. We did not also re-run JAGS with the better code. For the hardest case, BFG report JAGS being about 1.8 times more efficient than Stan and about 2.1 times more efficient than NIMBLE. In that case coding the model better makes NIMBLE 11.4 times more efficient, apparently more efficient than Stan and possibly than JAGS. Again, we did not run JAGS with and without the coding improvement. As a final example, in one of the middle LM-L cases, with N = 1000, p = 30, and 15 of those truly 0, Stan is reported by BFG to be about 3.6 times more efficient than NIMBLE. The better-coded model improves NIMBLE by about 1.7-fold, leaving it still behind Stan but only by about half as much.</p>
<p>We ran these comparisons on a MacBook Pro (2.4 GHz 8-Core Intel Core i9). It looks like this was roughly 5 times faster than the computer on which BFG ran.</p>
<p>Inspection of traceplots revealed that the traceplots for the variance in the 5th and 6th “LM-C” cases had not yet converged in the “BFG” version of the model. More burn-in iterations would be needed. This goes hand-in-hand with the recognition that NIMBLE benefits from good initial values. In a real analysis, if a long burn-in was observed, a practical step would be to provide better initial values for the next run. Applied analysis always involves multiple MCMC runs as one gets things working and checked. With the “better code” version, the chains do appear to have converged.</p>
<p>At this point we should highlight that <strong>there isn’t only one version of NIMBLE’s MCMC performance</strong>. NIMBLE’s MCMC system is highly configurable, and its default samplers are just one possible choice among many. When putting real effort into boosting performance for hard models, we’ve seen improvements by 1-3 orders of magnitude (<a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10651-016-0353-z">here</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.6053">here</a> and <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ecs2.3385">here</a>). In non-conjugate cases where JAGS performs well, it is worth noting that JAGS uses a lot of slice samplers, and those can also be configured in NIMBLE. (But the cases here use lots of conjugate samplers, rather than slice samplers.)</p>
<p>The takeaway is that we don’t know why BFG gave Stan the benefit of matrix multiplication but didn’t do so for JAGS or NIMBLE, and doing so makes a substantial difference for NIMBLE. Also, we see more conjugacy cases to catch in our symbolic processing of model relationships.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>tutorial</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/a-close-look-at-some-linear-model-mcmc-comparisons.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A close look at some posted trials of nimble for accelerated failure time models</title>
  <dc:creator>Perry de Valpine</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/a-close-look-at-some-posted-trials-of-nimble-for-accelerated-failure-time-models.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A bunch of folks have brought to our attention a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.09357">manuscript by Beraha, Falco and Guglielmi (BFG) posted on arXiv</a> giving some comparisons between JAGS, NIMBLE, and Stan. Naturally, we wanted to take a look. Each package performs best in some of their comparisons. There’s a lot going on, so here we’re just going to work through the last of their four examples, an accelerated failure time (AFT) model, because that’s the one where NIMBLE looks the worst in their results. The code from BFG is given on GitHub <a href="https://github.com/daniele-falco/software_comparison">here</a>.</p>
<p>There may be some issues with their other three examples as well, and we might work through those in future blog post(s). NIMBLE provides a lot of flexibility for configuring MCMCs in different ways (with different samplers), which means a comparison using our default configuration is just a start. Performance differences can also arise from writing the same model in different ways. We see both kinds of issues coming up for the other examples. But the AFT example gives a lot to talk about, so we’re sticking to that one here.</p>
<p>It turns out that NIMBLE and JAGS were put at a huge disadvantage compared to Stan, and that BFG’s results from NIMBLE don’t look valid, and that there isn’t any exploration of NIMBLE’s configurability. If we make the model for NIMBLE and JAGS comparable to the model for Stan, NIMBLE does roughly 2-45 times better in various cases than what BFG reported. If we explore a simple block sampling option, NIMBLE gets a small additional boost in some cases. It’s hard to compare results exactly with what BFG report, and we are not out to re-run the full comparison including JAGS and Stan. A “back of the envelope” comparison suggests that NIMBLE is still less efficient than Stan for this example, but not nearly to the degree reported. We’re also not out to explore many sampling configurations to try for better performance in this particular example problem, but part of NIMBLE’s design is to make it easy to do so.</p>
<p>Before starting into the AFT models, it’s worth recognizing that software benchmarks and other kinds of performance comparisons are really hard to do well. It’s almost inevitable that, when done by developers of one package, that package gets a boost in results even if objectivity is the honest goal. That’s because package developers almost can’t help using their package effectively and likely don’t know how to use other packages as well as their own. In this case, it’s fair to point out that NIMBLE needs more care in providing valid initial values (which BFG’s code doesn’t do) and that NIMBLE’s default samplers don’t work well here, which is because this problem features heavy right tails of Weibull distributions with shape parameter &lt; 1. For many users, that is not a typical problem. By choosing slice samplers (which JAGS often uses too) instead of NIMBLE’s default Metropolis-Hastings samplers, the mixing is much better. This issue is only relevant to the problem as BFG formulated it for JAGS and NIMBLE and goes away when we put it on par with the formulation BFG gave to Stan. In principle, comparisons by third parties, like BFG, might be more objective than those by package developers, but in this case the comparisons by BFG don’t use JAGS or NIMBLE effectively and include incorrect results from NIMBLE.</p>
<p>Below we try to reproduce their (invalid) results for NIMBLE and to run some within-NIMBLE comparisons of other methods. We’ll stick to their model scenarios and performance metrics. Those metrics are not the way we’ve done some published MCMC comparisons <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10651-016-0353-z">here</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.6053">here</a> and <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ecs2.3385">here</a>, but using them will allow readers to interpret our results alongside theirs.</p>
<p>First we’ll give a brief summary of their model scenarios. Here goes.</p>
<section id="accelerated-failure-time-aft-models" class="level1">
<h1>Accelerated Failure Time (AFT) models</h1>
<p>Here’s a lightning introduction to AFT models based on Weibull distributions. These are models for time-to-event data such as a “failure.” For shape <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a"> and scale <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s">, the Weibull probability density function for time <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t"> is</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f_W(t%20%7C%20a,%20s)%20=%20%5Cfrac%7Ba%7D%7Bs%7D%5Cleft(%5Cfrac%7Bt%7D%7Bs%7D%5Cright)%5E%7Ba-1%7D%20e%5E%7B-%5Cleft(%5Cfrac%7Bt%7D%7Bs%7D%5Cright)%5Ea%7D"></p>
<p>One important thing about the Weibull is that its cumulative density can be written in closed form. It is:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?F_W(t%20%7C%20a,%20s)%20=%201-e%5E%7B%5Cleft(%5Cfrac%7Bt%7D%7Bs%7D%5Cright)%5Ea%7D"></p>
<p>The role of covariates is to accelerate or decelerate the time course towards failure, effectively stretching or shrinking the time scale for each item. Specifically, for covariate vector <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?x"> and coefficient vector <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ceta">, define <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctheta%20=%20e%5E%7B-x'%20%5Ceta%7D">. Then the distribution of times-to-event is defined by rescaling the Weibull: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f(t%20%7C%20%5Ctheta,%20a,%20s)%20=%20%5Ctheta%20f_W(%5Ctheta%20t%20%7C%20a,%20s)">. This gives a Weibull with shape <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a"> and scale <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s%20/%20%5Ctheta">, so we have</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f(t%20%7C%20%5Ctheta,%20a,%20s)%20=%20f_W%5Cleft(t%20%7C%20a,%20%5Cfrac%7Bs%7D%7B%5Ctheta%7D%5Cright)"></p>
<p>In the code, there are two parameterizations in play. The first is <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(a,%20s)"> as just given. This is used in Stan and could be used in NIMBLE because it supports alternative parameterizations, including that one. Given <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ceta">, the scale is <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Clog(2)%5E%7B-%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Ba%7D%7D%20e%5E%7Bx'%20%5Ceta%7D">. The second is <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cleft(a,%20%5Clambda%20=%20%5Cleft(%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Bs%7D%5Cright)%5E%7Ba%7D%5Cright)">. This is the parameterization in the BUGS model language, so it is used in JAGS and is the default in NIMBLE. Given <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ceta">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Clambda%20=%20%5Clog(2)%20e%5E%7B-a(x'%20%5Ceta)%7D">.</p>
<p>The reason for the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Clog(2)"> is that it makes the median of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f_W(t%20%7C%20a,%20s)"> be 1 for any <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a">, i.e.&nbsp;when <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?x'%20%5Ceta%20=%200">. Priors are put on <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a"> (<code>alpha</code> in the code) and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ceta"> (<code>beta</code>). There is no separate scale parameter. Rather, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Clambda%20=%20%5Clog(2)"> when <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?x'%20%5Ceta%20=%200">. The models are equivalent with either parameterization, and they shouldn’t have much impact on computational efficiency. We’re just pointing them out to follow what’s going on.</p>
<section id="right-censored-failure-time-data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="right-censored-failure-time-data">Right-censored failure time data</h2>
<p>When a failure time is directly observed, its likelihood contribution is <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f_W(t%20%7C%20a,%20s%20e%5E%7Bx'%20%5Ceta%7D)">. When a unit hasn’t failed by its last observation, all that is known is that it lasted at least until <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t">. Then its likelihood contribution is <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1-F_W(t%20%7C%20a,%20s%20e%5E%7Bx'%20%5Ceta%7D)">. This is called a right-censored observation. Thus the data consist of some <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t">s that are actual failure times and some <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t">s that are right-censoring times.</p>
<p>There are two ways to handle a right-censored observation in MCMC:</p>
<ul>
<li>Include the likelihood factor <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1-F_W(t%20%7C%20a,%20s%20e%5E%7Bx'%20%5Ceta%7D)">. This is how BFG set up the model for Stan.</li>
<li>Include a latent state, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t'">, for the failure time. Include the likelihood factor <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f_W(t'%20%7C%20a,%20s%20e%5E%7Bx'%20%5Ceta%7D)"> and let MCMC sample <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t'">, with the numerical effect of integrating over it. This is how BFG set up the model for JAGS and NIMBLE.</li>
</ul>
<p>The first version is marginalized relative to the second version because <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1-F_W(t%20%7C%20a,%20s%20e%5E%7Bx'%20%5Ceta%7D)"> integrates over <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t'"> without needing to sample it. Often, but not always, marginalization is computationally faster and gives better mixing, so it makes the MCMC problem easier. That’s why the comparison as set up by BFG seems like an apples-to-oranges comparison. They’ve made the problem substantially easier for Stan.</p>
<p>It’s easy to set up the marginalized version for JAGS or NIMBLE. This can be done using the “zeroes” trick in the BUGS language, which both packages use for writing models. In NIMBLE this can also be done by writing a user-defined distribution as a <code>nimbleFunction</code>, which can be compiled along with a model.</p>
</section>
<section id="bfgs-scenarios" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bfgs-scenarios">BFG’s scenarios</h2>
<p>BFG included the following scenarios:</p>
<ul>
<li>Sample size, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?N">, is 100 or 1000.</li>
<li>Number of explanatory variables, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p">, is 4 or 16. These always include an intercept. Other covariates, and the true coefficient values, are simulated.</li>
<li>Censoring times are drawn from another Weibull distribution. This is set up following previous works such that the expected proportion of censored values is 20%, 50% or 80%.</li>
<li>Most of their comparisons use informative priors. Those are the ones we look at here. Again, we weren’t out to look at everything they did.</li>
<li>They used <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?N_%7Bit%7D%20=%2010,000"> total iterations. Of these, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?5,000"> were discarded as burn-in (warmup). They used a thinning interval of 2, resulting in <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?N_s%20=%202,500"> saved samples.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="some-issues-to-explore" class="level1">
<h1>Some issues to explore</h1>
<p>Now that we’ve set up the background, we are ready to list some of the issues with BFG’s comparisons that are worth exploring. For the computational experiments below, we decided to limit our efforts to NIMBLE because we are not trying to re-do BFG’s full analysis. Here are the main issues.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>BFG gave Stan a much easier problem than they gave JAGS and NIMBLE.</strong> Stan was allowed to use direct calculation of right-censored probabilities. These are complementary (right-tail) cumulative probability density calculations. NIMBLE and JAGS were made to sample latent failure times for censored items, even though they can be set up to use the cumulative calculations as well. Below we give NIMBLE a more comparable problem to the one given by BFG to Stan.</li>
<li><strong>It looks like BFG must not have obtained valid results from NIMBLE because they did not set up valid initial values for latent failure times.</strong> NIMBLE can be more sensitive to initial values (“inits”) than JAGS. We think that’s partly because NIMBLE uses a lot of adaptive random-walk Metropolis-Hastings samplers in its default MCMC configuration. In any case, NIMBLE gives warnings at multiple steps if a user should give attention to initial values. We give warnings instead of errors because a user might have plans to add initial values at a later step, and because sometimes MCMC samplers can recover from bad initial values. In the AFT example, the model does not “know” that initial values for latent failure times must be greater than the censoring times. If they aren’t, the likelihood calculations will return a <code>-Inf</code> (or possibly <code>NA</code>), which causes trouble for the samplers. Inspection of the model after MCMC runs using BFG’s code shows that even after 10000 iterations, the model likelihood is <code>-Inf</code>, so the results are invalid. It’s fair to say this is an issue in how to use NIMBLE, but it’s confusing to include invalid results in a comparison.</li>
<li><strong>Even with valid initial values in BFG’s model formulation, NIMBLE’s default samplers do not do well for this example. In this post, we explore slice samplers instead.</strong> The problem is that the Weibull distributions in these scenarios give long right tails, due to simulating with shape parameter &lt; 1. This corresponds to failure rates that decrease with time, like when many failures occur early and then those that don’t fail can last a long, long time. MCMC sampling of long right tails is a known challenge. In trial runs, we saw that, to some extent, the issue can be diagnosed by monitoring the latent failure times and noticing that they don’t mix well. We also saw that sometimes regression parameters displayed mixing problems. BFG report that NIMBLE’s results have mean posterior values farther from the correct values than given by the other tools, which is a hint that something is more deeply wrong. Slice samplers work much better for this situation, and it is easy to tell NIMBLE to use slice samplers, which we did.</li>
<li><strong>BFG’s code uses matrix multiplication for <code>X%*%eta</code> in Stan, but not in NIMBLE or JAGS, even though they also support matrix multiplication.</strong> Instead, BFG’s code for NIMBLE and JAGS has a scalar declaration for each element of the matrix multiplication operation, followed by the sums that form each element of the result. We modify the code to use matrix multiplication. While we don’t often see this make a huge difference in run-time performance (when we’ve looked at the issue in other examples), it could potentially matter, and it definitely speeds up NIMBLE’s model-building and compilation steps because there is less to keep track of. An intermediate option would be to use inner products (<code>inprod</code>).</li>
<li>It’s worth noting that <em>all of these examples are fairly fast and mix fairly well</em>. Some might disagree, but these all generate reasonable effective sample sizes in seconds-to-minutes, not hours-to-days.</li>
<li>There are some minor issues, and we don’t want to get nit-picky. One is that we don’t see BFG’s code being set up to be reproducible. For example, not only is there no <code>set.seed</code> so that others can generate identical data sets, but it looks like <em>each package was given different simulated data sets</em>. It can happen that MCMC performance depends on the data set. While this <em>might</em> not be a huge issue, we prefer below to give each package the same, reproducible, data sets. Another issue is that looking at <em>average</em> effective sample size across parameters can be misleading because one wants all parameters mixed well, not some mixed really well and others mixed poorly. But in these examples the parameters compared are all regression-type coefficients that play similar roles in the model, and the averaging doesn’t look like a huge issue. Finally, BFG decline to report ESS/time, preferring instead to report ESS and time and let readers make sense of them. We see ESS/time as the primary metric of interest, the number of effectively independent samples generated per second, so we report it below. This gives a way to see how both mixing (ESS) and computation time contribute to MCMC performance.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="setting-up-the-example" class="level1">
<h1>Setting up the example</h1>
<p>We use BFG’s code but modify it to organize it into functions and make it reproducible. The <a href="https://github.com/nimble-dev/nimble-demos/tree/master/blog_posts/AFT_comparisons_Behara_etal">source files</a> for this document includes code chunks to run and save results. We are not running JAGS or Stan because we are not trying to reproduce a full set of comparisons. Instead we are looking into NIMBLE’s performance for this example. Since the main issue is that BFG gave NIMBLE and JAGS harder models than they gave Stan, we fix this in a way that is not NIMBLE-specific and should also work for JAGS.</p>
<p>Here is a summary of what the code does:</p>
<ul>
<li>Set up the twelve cases with informative priors included in the first twelve rows of BFG’s table 5, which has their AFT results.</li>
<li>For each of the twelve cases, run:
<ul>
<li>the original method of BFG, which gives <strong>invalid</strong> results but is useful for trying to see how much later steps improve over what BFG reported;</li>
<li>a method with valid initial values and slice sampling, but still in the harder model formulation given by BFG;</li>
<li>a method with the model formulation matching what BFG gave to Stan, using marginal probabilities for censored times and also using matrix multiplication;</li>
<li>a method with the model formulation matching what BFG gave to Stan and also with one simple experiment in block sampling. The block sampler used is a multivariate adaptive random-walk Metropolis-Hastings sampler for all the regression coefficients. It sometimes helps to let these try multiple propose-accept/reject steps because otherwise <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p"> tries are replaced with 1 try (where <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p">) is the number of regression coefficients). As a heuristic choice, we used <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p/2"> tries each time the sampler ran.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Although the original method of BFG seems to give invalid results, we include it so we can try to roughly compare performance (shown below) against what they report. However one difficulty is that processing with <code>-Inf</code> and <code>NaN</code> values can be substantially slower than processing with actual numbers, and these issues might differ across systems.</p>
<p>Results here are run on a MacBook Pro (2019), with 2.4 GHz 8-Core Intel Core i9, and OS X version 11.6.</p>
</section>
<section id="results" class="level1">
<h1>Results</h1>
<p>Here are the results, in a table that roughly matches the format of BFG’s Table 5. “Perc” is the average fraction of observations that are right-censored.</p>
<p>As best as we can determine:</p>
<ul>
<li>“ESS/Ns” is their “ε_η”. This is the mean effective sample size of the (4 or 16) beta coefficients per saved MCMC iteration. The number of saved iterations, N_s is 2500. We used <code>coda::effectiveSize</code> to estimate ESS. We did not see in their code what method they used. This is another reason we can’t be sure how to compare our results to theirs.</li>
<li>“Nit/t” is their “N_it/t_s”, total number of iterations (10000) per computation time, not counting compilation time.</li>
<li>We calculate “ESS/t”, which is the product of the previous two numbers divided by four, (ESS/Ns)*(Nit/t)/4. This is the mean effective sample size from the saved samples per total sampling time (including burn-in). One might also consider modifying this for the burn-in portion. The factor 4 comes from N_it/N_s = 4. We do it this way to make it easier to compare to BFG’s Table 5. They decline to calculate a metric of ESS per time, which we view as a fundamental metric of MCMC performance. An MCMC can be efficient either by generating well-mixed samples at high computational cost or generating poorly-mixed samples at low computational cost, so both mixing and computational cost contribute to MCMC efficiency.</li>
</ul>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;">BFG (invalid)</th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;">BFG+inits+slice</th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;">Marginal</th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;">Marginal+blocks</th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
<th style="text-align: right;"></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;">ESS/Ns</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">Nit/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">ESS/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">ESS/Ns</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">Nit/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">ESS/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">ESS/Ns</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">Nit/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">ESS/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">ESS/Ns</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">Nit/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">ESS/t</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Perc = 0.2</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=100, p = 4, perc = 0.2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.27</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">6844.63</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">465.80</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.52</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2325.58</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">300.65</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.39</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">9775.17</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">951.09</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.27</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">16233.77</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1109.06</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=1000, p = 4, perc = 0.2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.30</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1127.27</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">84.71</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.55</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">306.22</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">41.83</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.41</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1527.88</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">157.65</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.28</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2490.04</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">171.47</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=100, p = 16, perc = 0.2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.19</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3423.49</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">161.60</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.36</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">949.49</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">84.94</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.27</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3717.47</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">248.99</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.29</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5621.14</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">408.77</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=1000, p = 16, perc = 0.2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.08</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">404.22</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">7.80</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.57</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">98.86</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">14.16</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.41</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">591.82</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">61.12</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.30</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1100.47</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">83.33</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Perc = 0.5</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=100, p = 4, perc = 0.5</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.05</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">7262.16</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">98.39</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.08</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2572.68</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">54.45</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.38</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">10214.50</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">960.31</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.26</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">15060.24</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">990.34</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=1000, p = 4, perc = 0.5</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.10</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1106.32</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">26.96</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.10</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">298.23</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">7.25</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.44</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1987.28</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">219.92</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.26</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3074.09</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">196.19</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=100, p = 16, perc = 0.5</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.06</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3411.80</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">52.07</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.21</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">940.56</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">49.94</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.23</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3955.70</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">229.94</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.28</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5854.80</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">415.89</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=1000, p = 16, perc = 0.5</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.07</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">339.29</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5.88</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.07</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">95.90</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.66</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.41</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">601.90</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">61.98</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.31</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1074.58</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">83.07</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Perc = 0.8</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=100, p = 4, perc = 0.8</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.03</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">6761.33</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">51.99</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.02</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2297.79</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">10.79</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.24</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">9842.52</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">602.28</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.20</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">15151.52</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">763.36</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=1000, p = 4, perc = 0.8</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.02</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1013.27</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5.16</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.02</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">265.58</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.50</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.39</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1831.50</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">180.50</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.25</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2856.33</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">176.27</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=100, p = 16, perc = 0.8</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.04</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3412.97</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">33.45</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.03</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">876.96</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">6.74</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.17</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3853.56</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">166.26</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.23</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5820.72</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">329.18</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">N=1000, p = 16, perc = 0.8</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.01</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">395.99</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.22</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.05</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">95.33</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1.22</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.39</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">560.54</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">54.91</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0.29</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1016.57</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">72.55</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The left-most set of results (“BFG (invalid)”) is comparable to the right-most (“NIMBLE”) column of BFG’s Table 5, in the same row order for their first 12 rows. The simulated data sets are different. For that reason and the stochasticity of Monte Carlo methods, we shouldn’t expect to see exactly matching values. And of course the computations were run on different systems, resulting in different times. Again, these results are <strong>invalid</strong>.</p>
<p>The next column (“BFG+inits+slice”) gives results when BFG’s model formulation for JAGS and NIMBLE is combined with valid initialization and slice sampling in NIMBLE. We can see that valid sampling generally gives lower ESS/time than the invalid results.</p>
<p>The next column shows results when the problem is set up as BFG gave it to Stan, and NIMBLE’s default samplers are used. If we assume the left-most results are similar to what BFG report, but with times from the system used here, then the boost in performance is the ratio of ESS/time between methods. For example, in the last row, the marginal method is 54.91/1.22 = 45.01 times more efficient that what BFG reported. We can make a similar kind of ratio between Stan and NIMBLE from BFG’s results, which gave Stan as about 380 times more efficient than NIMBLE (although rounding error for “1%” could be a substantial issue here). Putting these together, Stan might really be about 8.4 times more efficient than NIMBLE for this case, which is the hardest case considered.</p>
<p>The last column shows results of the single experiment with alternative (block) samplers that we tried. In many cases, it gives a modest additional boost. Often with more work one can find a better sampling strategy, which can be worth the trouble for extended work with a particular kind of model. In the last row of our results, this gives about another 72.55 / 54.91 = 1.32 boost in performance, lowering the ratio to Stan to about 6.4. Again, we decided to limit this post to within-NIMBLE comparisons, and the comparisons to Stan based on BFG’s results should be taken with a grain of salt because we didn’t re-run them.</p>
<p>In summary, it looks like BFG gave Stan a different and easier accelerated failure time problem than they gave NIMBLE and JAGS. When given the same problem as they gave Stan, NIMBLE’s default samplers perform around 2 to 45 times better than what BFG reported.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>tutorial</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/a-close-look-at-some-posted-trials-of-nimble-for-accelerated-failure-time-models.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>NIMBLE online tutorial, November 18, 2021</title>
  <dc:creator>Chris Paciorek</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/nimble-online-tutorial-november-18-2021.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ll be giving a two-hour tutorial on NIMBLE, sponsored by the environmental Bayes (enviBayes) section of ISBA (The International Society for Bayesian Analysis), on Thursday November 18, from 11 am to 1 pm US Eastern time.</p>
<p>NIMBLE (<a href="http://r-nimble.org/">r-nimble.org</a>) is a system for fitting and programming with hierarchical models in R that builds on (a new implementation of) the BUGS language for declaring models. NIMBLE provides analysts with a flexible system for using MCMC, sequential Monte Carlo, MCEM, and other techniques on user-specified models. It provides developers and methodologists with the ability to write algorithms in an R-like syntax that can be easily disseminated to users. C++ versions of models and algorithms are created for speed, but these are manipulated from R without any need for analysts or algorithm developers to program in C++. While analysts can use NIMBLE as a nearly drop-in replacement for WinBUGS or JAGS, NIMBLE provides enhanced functionality in a number of ways.</p>
<p>This workshop will demonstrate how one can use NIMBLE to:</p>
<ul>
<li>flexibly specify an MCMC for a specific model, including choosing samplers and blocking approaches (and noting the potential usefulness of this for teaching);</li>
<li>tailor an MCMC to a specific model using user-defined distributions, user-defined functions, and vectorization;</li>
<li>write your own MCMC sampling algorithms and use them in combination with samplers from NIMBLE’s library of samplers;</li>
<li>develop and disseminate your own algorithms, building upon NIMBLE’s existing algorithms; and</li>
<li>use specialized model components such as Dirichlet processes, conditional auto-regressive (CAR) models, and reversible jump for variable selection.</li>
</ul>
<p>The tutorial will assume working knowledge of hierarchical models and some familiarity with MCMC. Given the two-hour time frame, we’ll focus on demonstrating some of the key features of NIMBLE, without going into a lot of detail on any given topic.</p>
<p>To attend, please register <a href="https://uci.zoom.us/meeting/register/tJwkf-CvrzsoG9YNWKAJvkTzgYPUaYzPChef">here</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>education</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/nimble-online-tutorial-november-18-2021.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Version 0.12.1 of NIMBLE released</title>
  <dc:creator>NIMBLE Development Team</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-0-12-1-of-nimble-released.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’ve released the newest version of NIMBLE on CRAN and on our website. NIMBLE is a system for building and sharing analysis methods for statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods (such as MCMC and SMC).</p>
<p>Version 0.12.1, in combination with version 0.12.0 (which was released just last week), provides a variety of new functionality (in particular enhanced WAIC functionality and adding the LKJ distribution) plus bug fixes affecting MCMC in specific narrow cases described below and that warrant upgrading for some users. The changes include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Completely revamping WAIC in NIMBLE, creating an online version that does not require any particular variable monitors. The new WAIC can calculate conditional or marginal WAIC and can group data nodes into joint likelihood terms if desired. In addition there is a new <code>calculateWAIC()</code> function that will calculate the basic conditional WAIC from MCMC output without having to enable the WAIC when creating the MCMC.</li>
<li>Adding the LKJ distribution, useful for prior distributions for correlation matrices, along with random walk samplers for them. These samplers operate in an unconstrained transformed parameter space and are assigned by default during MCMC configuration.</li>
<li>Fixing a bug introduced in conjugacy processing in version 0.11.0 that causes incorrect MCMC sampling only in specific cases. The impacted cases have terms of the form <code>a[i] + x[i] * beta</code> (or more simply <code>x[i] * beta</code>), with <code>beta</code> subject to conjugate sampling and either (i) <code>x</code> provided via NIMBLE’s <code>constants</code> argument and <code>x[1] == 1</code> or (ii) <code>a</code> provided via NIMBLE’s <code>constants</code> argument and <code>a[1] == 0</code>.</li>
<li>Fixing an error in the sampler for the proper CAR distribution (<code>dcar_proper</code>) that gives incorrect MCMC results when the mean of the proper CAR is not the same value for all locations, e.g., when embedding covariate effects directly in the <code>mu</code> parameter of the <code>dcar_proper</code> distribution.</li>
<li>Fixing <code>isData("y")</code> to return <code>TRUE</code> whenever any elements of a multivariate data node (<code>y</code>) are flagged as data. As a result, attempting to carry out MCMC on the non-data elements will now fail. Formerly if only some elements were flagged as data, <code>isData</code> would only check the first element, potentially leading to other elements that were flagged as data being overwritten.</li>
<li>Error trapping cases where a BNP model has a differing number of dependent stochastic nodes (e.g., observations) or dependent deterministic nodes per group of elements clustered jointly (using functionality introduced in version 0.10.0). Previously we were not error trapping this, and incorrect MCMC results would be obtained.</li>
<li>Improving the formatting of standard logging messages.</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>release</category>
  <category>announcement</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://r-nimble.org/blog/version-0-12-1-of-nimble-released.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
